<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-05-29T23:42:44-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">The Intelligence Transition</title><subtitle>Thoughts on AI, papers, tools, and experiments</subtitle><entry><title type="html">The Singularity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/24/the-singularity/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Singularity" /><published>2025-05-24T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2025-05-24T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/24/the-singularity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/24/the-singularity/"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p><strong>The Singularity</strong> (n.): The moment when artificial intelligence progresses so rapidly that we can no longer predict or comprehend its trajectory. A technological tipping point where AI systems become capable of recursive self-improvement, fundamentally altering the nature of progress itself.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hello. My name is Anton.</p>

<p>I’m a Site Reliability Engineer, with a background in Quality Engineering, and Software Engineering.</p>

<p>I’m also a big nerd.</p>

<p>I don’t expect this to be read by anyone but me, but I hope it might resonate with someone who shares the same curiosity about what we’re building and where we’re headed. We’re living through something unprecedented, and it deserves to be witnessed and recorded.</p>

<p>November 2022 marked the beginning of a new chapter in my life. The release of ChatGPT was the moment I could suddenly talk to artificial intelligence and receive responses that were both coherent and genuinely intelligent. The conversations felt real in a way that previous AI interactions never had.</p>

<h2 id="beyond-the-turing-test">Beyond the Turing Test</h2>

<p>In the subsequent months and years, we’ve quietly blown past the Turing Test. I expected this to be a massively celebrated achievement. Instead, it came and went without so much as a collective shout-out. The goalpost simply moved.
We spent decades defining machine intelligence by whether it could fool us into thinking it was human, yet when that barrier fell, we barely even blinked.</p>

<h2 id="the-scale-of-this-transition">The Scale of This Transition</h2>

<p>I’ve come to think of this period as analogous to The Industrial Revolution: automated labor, allowing machines to exceed what human muscle could achieve. Machines could lift more, work longer, and operate more precisely than human muscle ever could.</p>

<p>I think what we’re experiencing now is the approach to the Singularity: the moment when AI becomes capable of improving itself faster than we can understand or control. We’re building systems that don’t just complement human intelligence, but may soon surpass our ability to keep pace with their development.</p>

<h2 id="embracing-uncertainty">Embracing Uncertainty</h2>

<p>I’ve gone from thinking I had a reasonable sense of what the future held to realizing it has become fundamentally impossible to predict. Had you told me five years ago that we would have this level of conversational AI in a matter of years, I wouldn’t have believed you. The exponential nature of AI progress suggests we’re approaching a singularity - a point where technological advancement becomes so rapid and unpredictable that we can no longer meaningfully forecast what comes next.</p>

<p>This uncertainty has given me profound hope (… and a lot of anxiety). Problems that once seemed insurmountable (the nature of reality, space travel, disease, understanding the universe) may be solvable. We may no longer be bottlenecked waiting for the next Einstein to emerge naturally. We might be building systems that can think at superhuman levels across every domain simultaneously.</p>

<h2 id="why-this-blog-exists">Why This Blog Exists</h2>

<p>I don’t know what our future will look like, but I feel a deep sense of wonder and excitement about finding out. This blog exists to document that journey.</p>

<p>I’m here to witness the progress we’re making, as a curious and open-minded observer.</p>]]></content><author><name>Anton</name></author><category term="singularity" /><category term="ai-capabilities" /><category term="meta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The Singularity (n.): The moment when artificial intelligence progresses so rapidly that we can no longer predict or comprehend its trajectory. A technological tipping point where AI systems become capable of recursive self-improvement, fundamentally altering the nature of progress itself.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Setting up this blog</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/24/first-post/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Setting up this blog" /><published>2025-05-24T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2025-05-24T00:00:00-03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/05/24/first-post</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/05/24/first-post/"><![CDATA[<p>The setup is pretty minimal - Jekyll on GitHub Pages with a dark theme that I actually like looking at. Should make it easy to just drop markdown files here whenever I want to write about:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Papers I’ve read</li>
  <li>Tools I’m experimenting with</li>
  <li>Random AI thoughts and observations</li>
  <li>Code experiments and results</li>
  <li>The implications of AI</li>
</ul>

<p>Let’s see if styling works:</p>

<h2 id="code-blocks-work-nicely">Code blocks work nicely</h2>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">hello_ai</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Ready to write about AI stuff!</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p><strong>Bold text</strong> and <em>italic text</em> look good. Links should work too.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Block quotes for when I want to highlight something important from a paper</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Time to start writing actual content!</p>]]></content><author><name>Anton</name></author><category term="meta" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The setup is pretty minimal - Jekyll on GitHub Pages with a dark theme that I actually like looking at. Should make it easy to just drop markdown files here whenever I want to write about:]]></summary></entry></feed>